### CURRICULUM VITAE DOREEN KAGAI LUGALIA

#### PERSONAL DETAILS

DATE OF BIRTH: 20 FEBRUARY 1971

ADDRESS: P.O.BOX 35501 - 00 200, NAIROBI

TELEPHONE: +254(0722 952730, 0733 794370,

E-Mail: <u>Doreen.Lugalia@Unilever.com</u>; <u>dlugalia@yahoo.com</u>

#### PERSONALITY PROFILE

I am a highly motivated and enthusiastic individual capable of handling tasks with great attention to detail. I have pleasant character and I am a team player. I have vast experience in the Supply Chain Organization.

I am also an excellent trainer and have implemented Quality, Food Safety, Occupational Health & Safety and Environmental Management Systems and have a passion to disseminate information on the difference Management Systems can make to a business.

#### **EDUCATION**

2000: UNIVERSITY OF NAIROBI – Master of Science in Food Science and Technology. Title of

research project: "Development of a weaning food using blends of sweetpotato and cereal

flours".

1994: UNIVERSITY OF NAIROBI – Bachelor of Science in Food Science and Technology (Upper

Second Class Honours).

1989: ALLIANCE GIRLS' HIGH SCHOOL - Kenya Advanced Certificate of Education (3

Principals, 1 Subsidiary)

1987: ALLIANCE GIRLS' HIGH SCHOOL – Kenya Certificate of Education (Division 1, 12 points)

1983: HIGHRIDGE PRIMARY SCHOOL – Certificate of Primary Education (35 points)

#### **OTHERS**

Certified Public Accountant, Part One – Section One. ISO 9001:2000 Lead Auditor, transition to ISO 9001:2015 Dale Carnegie ® Course FSSC 22000 Lead Auditor – SGS (K) Ltd. Currently pursuing CPIM

#### **COMPUTER LITERACY**

Excellent knowledge of MS Office, Statistical Package for Social Sciences (SPSS)

#### PROFESSIONAL AFFILIATIONS

Associate Member, American Society for Quality.

Trainer in Food Safety & Occupational Health & Safety Management Systems – National Quality Institute – Kenya Bureau of Standards

Member - Technical Committees on Food Hygiene and Labelling of Pre-packaged foods

Member - Professional Trainers Association of Kenya

#### WORK EXPERIENCE

#### April 2019 to date

## Quality Assurance Manager, KENCHIC LTD. (also responsible for two Plants in Zambia and Tanzania)

To implement the Food Safety & Quality Management Systems to ensure that all products are manufactured and delivered according to set standards.

To implement Customer Specific Management Systems and drive every day Quality execution and continuous improvement.

#### July 2018 to April 2019

Managing Consultant, Mantra Quality Consulting Ltd.

Training and Consultation in implementation of Quality, Food Safety and Occupational Health & Safety to a myriad of Clients.

- Unilever (K). Ltd. Tea Buying Division
- Unicool Ltd.
- Kenya Nut Company
- Ultimate Engineering Ltd.

#### February 2016 to July 2018

SHE Manager, East Africa.

Driving the implementation of Safety Health and Environment in the Sites in East Africa (including Ethiopia)

- Safety Pillar lead World Class Manufacturing
- Strategic initiatives to deliver Vision Zero within Unilever East Africa.
- Behavioral Safety Trainer

#### December 2013 to January 2016.

Product Group Quality Manager, HPC - Africa, Unilever (K) Ltd.

Supports sites located in East Africa, West Africa, South Africa and Southern Africa in the following areas:

- Provide technical (category) support and expertise to factories, Regional Virtual Sites, Third Party Manufacturers and Suppliers for capability assessment, innovation execution, QMS application, early equipment mgt
- Drive Quality improvement in Regional Category Leadership Teams and connect improvements across sites
- Drive the Quality Agenda in new factory and acquisition integration and start up
- I took a challenging role as the Chair of the Shadow Board and led the implementation of an alternative channel of sales by introducing entrepreneurs to distribute Unilever Products. This initiative resulted in an introduction of sales of approximately Kshs 1million per month.

#### July 2010 to November 2013

Quality Support Manager, Diageo Africa Supply, East and Southern Africa Hub. working at East African Breweries Ltd.

Providing support to the following sites in implementation of Management Systems (Food Safety, Quality, Environmental, Occupational Health & Safety):

- Tusker Brewery (Kenya)
- UDV Spirits plant
- East African Maltings
- Central Glass Industries
- Serengeti Brewery (Tanzania)
- Uganda Breweries
- Seychelles Brewery
- Brandhouse (a spirits blending plant, South Africa)

# From July 2013, I worked as the Quality Sustainability Lead in the Perfect Plant Management System (PPMS) Quality Work- stream to enable embedding the Diageo Perfect Plant System in Tusker Brewery.

- Integration of Serengeti Breweries with three sites in Tanzania, and preparation for the implementation of Quality Management Systems and Food Safety System Certification.
- I am currently leading the implementation of FSSC 22000 certification at Tusker site
- Served as the project lead and successfully implemented the UNILAB Laboratory Information Management System.
- Led the successful certification of SBL Dar brewery to ISO 9001:2008 at their first attempt
- Preparing training material and delivering training to all sites on all the Management Systems.
- I have twice led the Specification review exercise
- Driving improvement in site indices, management of non-conformances and concessions across the sites. Carrying out root cause analysis and problem solving.
- Part of the Quality Transformation Team
- Support the Implementation of corrective action plans
- Implementation of initiatives at the various sites from the Global Beer Technical Centre e.g. Global Finished Product Quality Standard, a packaging metric.
- I also participate as ta Site Sensory panelist and have consistently obtained an average score of >90% in the Taster Validation Scheme.

#### Sept. 2007 – July 2010: OSHE Manager, Kenya Wine Agencies Limited

To provide direction, ensure implementation and compliance of all Quality, Safety, Health & Environmental standards in the company

During my tenure I managed to oversee the following:

- Successful Job Evaluation Exercise
- Collation of the Performance contracting reports
- Create awareness on the impact of Quality in a business in line with its strategy, particularly on the development of competent staff
- Ensured the compliance to the requirements of the Occupational Health & Safety Act (OSHA) and Environment Management & Co-ordination Act (EMCA), and ensured compliance of contractors to both acts.
- Defined and determined the measurement of departmental objectives in line with the strategic objectives of the company.
- Developed an electronic system for the storage of all documentation policies, procedures, work instructions and forms.
- Developed a documented product development process (incorporating Customer expectations, feedback and consumer research
- Initiated a monthly report on non-conformances and customer complaints
- Introduced a branch wide audit and trained the Sales & Marketing team on addressing key issues related customer returns and handling of nonconforming products
- Member of the team that validated the NACADA guidelines on handling drug and substance abuse at the workplace.

## 2002 – August 2007 Quality Assurance Officer, The Mater Hospital. Reporting to the Chief Executive Officer, my duties included:

- Ensured maintenance of certification of the first hospital in East and Central Africa that was certified to a Quality Management System
- Monitor auditor performance and develop and maintain a competent team of auditors.
- Development and dissemination of Policies across all areas of operation including the Corporate Social Responsibility aspects.
- Management of the hospital's social responsibility activities such as Free Breast Screening camps, Medical Camps, Donation activities at the nearby Mukuru slum.

- Team leader of the Customer Satisfaction Measurement Project introduced the monitoring and analysis of customer expectations and feedback
- Team leader of Environmental Health and Safety Team addressing Occupational Health and Safety issues as well, incident/accident reporting, root cause analysis, etc
- Team leader of the implementation of the Cleaner Enterprise Programme at the hospital.
- Editor of the In-house magazine as well as any other communication material (marketing brochures)
- Overseeing the Catering function, which is currently outsourced, including auditing the supplier.
- Event management activities for cocktails, graduation parties, media briefings, etc
- Training and development of competence frameworks for all categories of staff.

**2000 – 2002: Consultant, Intersoft Limited**. My duties involved training and implementation of Quality Management Systems primarily ISO 9000:2000 and HACCP to a wide assortment of clients both in the manufacturing and service sectors. I was involved in the design of the various courses tailored to the clients' specific requirements.

#### My clients included:

- Brookside Dairy ISO 9001:2000 and HACCP implementation
- Farmer's Choice Limited HACCP implementation
- KAPA Oil Refineries Limited ISO 9001:2000 and HACCP implementation
- The Mater Hospital ISO 9001:2000 and HACCP implementation
- Wananchi Online Limited ISO 9001:2000 implementation
- Openview Business Systems ISO 9001:2000 implementation
- The Nairobi Hospital ISO 9001:2000 pre-assessment audit
- Mediplus Services Limited ISO 9001:2000 implementation
- Aga Khan Hospital Training on HACCP implementation
- Kenya Breweries and Kenya Maltings Limited Training on HACCP implementation

**1998 – 2000:** Research Assistant, SMALLFOOD Project on "Removing Constraints to the Development of Small Scale food Processing Enterprises in sub-Saharan Africa", a project funded by the European Union with partners in Zimbabwe and Cameroon and Co-ordinators in United Kingdom and France. Key products in Kenya were Dairy, Cassava and Maize, and the research involved producers, marketing agents, processors and consumers. The project was primarily aimed at finding the constraints that hamper development of these specific industries with a view to enhancing their presence and sustenance in the economy.

#### My duties included:

- General office administration (finances, secretarial duties, general correspondence)
- Organisation and execution of the data collection exercise, which involved design and administration of questionnaires to the various research groups.
- Analysis of data
- Report writing and dissemination
- Organisation of workshops and meetings with the partners and co-ordinators, as well as the various stakeholders.

## 1995 – 1996: Management Trainee, Brooke Bond (K) Ltd, then promoted to Assistant Technical Development Manager.

My duties included the following:

- Carrying out research projects in partnership with the parent research centre in the United Kingdom
- Providing relevant technical support to the eight tea processing factories
- Carrying out pilot projects during any course of factory development right through to commissioning at the factory.
- Carrying out modular training as well as training on Total Quality Management of Factory Staff
- Developing annual budgets for the Technical Development Factories.
- Pioneered in the selling of tea in other markets apart from the traditional Mombasa auction.

#### Part time lecturer at the Kenva Polytechnic.

Teaching "Technology of Specific Products" to students studying both Ordinary and Higher Diploma

#### Industrial Attachment at Kenya Breweries Limited

 Familiarisation with production, quality control and marketing procedures relating to beer, barley syrup and malt production

April – June. 1991 Audit Assistant, Coopers & Lybrand

Jan. – July 1990 Audit Assistant, Coopers & Lybrand

#### SEMINARS AND COURSES ATTENDED

- ISO 22000:2005 Lead Auditor SGS International (K) Ltd.
- Beer Sensory Training FlavorActiv. Ltd.
- Project Management Strathmore Business School
- Training of Trainers Food Safety and Occupational Health & Safety Management Systems National Quality Institute, Kenya Bureau of Standards
- Performance Management Public Sector Reforms & Performance Contracting
- Service Level Agreements Seminar CIAR Management Institute
- Occupational Health & Safety Workshop Federation of Kenya Employers
- Finance for Non-Finance Managers Manpower Training Consultants
- Performance Management & Appraisal Training Liam Consultants
- Prevention and Detection of Corporate Fraud Fraudstop
- Implementing an Environmental Management System KEBS
- Corporate Planning Seminar Management By Objectives
- Balanced Scorecard Seminar Strategic Leadership Centre
- Customer Satisfaction Workshop CVA International/Business Edge
- ISO 9001:2000 Lead Auditor Course CVA International/Business Edge.
- Implementing ISO 9001:2000 Intersoft Limited
- Process Auditing Skills Intersoft Limited
- Food Management Hebrew University of Jerusalem, Israel (submitted a project paper that was rated excellent).
- Total Quality Management Brooke Bond (K) Ltd
- Supervisory Skills Development Mayaka Management Training & Consultancy
- Making Effective Presentations Knowhow International Training
- Modern Management Techniques WorldAhead International Limited
- Training modules on Tea processing Brooke Bond (K) Ltd
- Brewing for Non-brewers Kenya Breweries Limited

#### OTHER ACTIVITIES AND HONOURS AWARDED

- Key member of the team that carried out the Job Evaluation Exercise at Kenya Wine Agencies Limited
- Prepared the write up that won The Mater Hospital first prize in the Leadership Category of the "Afya Excellence in Health Awards in 2006.
- Successfully organized the first Clean up Exercise (in the Mukuru/South B area) during the World Environmental Day Celebrations
- Member of the Supervisory Committee, Mater SACCO, organized and was part of the resource person during their Strategic Planning Workshop.
- Prepared the write up that won The Mater Hospital first prize (Large Organizations dealing in Services) in The Kenya Quality Award Competition, 2003, organized by The Kenya Bureau of Standards.
- Won a pick up truck in the "Hands On" competition, a test of patience and endurance.
- Awarded two prizes for the best student in Food Science and Technology
- University's Dean's list for second year students 1993
- Residence Hall Management from 1990 to 1994, first as a member then as Chairperson at the University of Nairobi
- Committee member of the Food Science Club

- School Prefect at Secondary and High School
- Treasurer of the Journalism Club
- Member of the Drama Clubs at Primary and Secondary through to High School
- Second Runner up in a Public Speaking Contest in Primary School

#### **REFEREES**

Mr. James Gathage **Managing Director** Quality Plus Limited P.O.Box 30068 00100 NAIROBI Tel. 0722 316 371,

E-mail: <a href="mailto:jmgathage@yahoo.com">jmgathage@yahoo.com</a>

Benard Ojil **Managing Consultant BEAM Consultants** P.O.Box 8724 00100 NAIROBI

Tel: 0721 805065

Email bcojil@yahoo.com

Gerald Makau Masila **Executive Director** Eastern Africa Grain Council P.O. Box 5137 - 00506 Nairobi

Tel: 0722 516250

Email: gmasila@eagc.org